the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform hello everyone I'm Dr Andy
Galpin I'm a professor of Kinesiology
and the center for sport performance at
Cal State Fullerton in today's show
we're going to be talking about sleep
performance now I like the term sleep
performance to really indicate the
difference between going from good sleep
to great sleep and so what I don't want
to spend much time on today is talking
about things like complete sleep
deprivation so what happens to physical
performance when you go 24 hours or 48
straight hours without sleep I don't
even really want to talk about what I'll
call Extreme sleep restriction so
sleeping for two hours a night you know
four hours a night things like that or
even a single bad night asleep what I
really want to spend most of our time
here talking about is what really
happens does anything happen when I go
from 6 or 7 hours of sleep to 8 or 9 how
much of a competitive Advantage am I
getting over other high performers when
I can go from that good to great sleep
we're also going to talk about why you
should be approaching your sleep with
the same Vigor and specificity as you're
doing your nutrition or your exercise
training I mean kind of think about it
this way if you are trying to perform
your absolute highest and you had the
resources or if you simply look at the
model for those individuals who do you
would see that they have dedicated
Professionals for high performance
nutrition you probably have done or
would do rather some sort of extensive
blood work or testing so that you can
get the best nutrition supplementation
for your unique body we would take a
similar approach right some sort of
advanced testing perhaps and an
individualized program that is being
modified and adapted as our goals are
changing as our body is responding as we
move throughout our life now in the
sport performance world we kind of call
this periodization so this is a phrase
where we have different volumes or
intensities or exercises and goals based
upon different phases of the Year trying
to get to specific outcome we wouldn't
necessarily eat the same thing every day
if our training wasn't the same we would
adjust our food intake or our calories
we would have more volume in our
workouts we'd have less volume we would
have more days off less recovery and
everything else that goes into this so
you see what I'm getting at here right
this is the idea that what we eat and
how we train are highly responsive and
adaptive to both our unique physiology
as well as what we're expecting out of
our body why do we not have the same
approach with sleep well the answer is
we can and in fact I'll try to convince
you here that we should we should be
taking the same level of specificity and
precision with our sleep our plan and
protocols should be adapting and
changing based on how our body is
responding and what we're asking our
body to do now as you can probably tell
I'm so fired up about this I'm doing my
best to mentally go slow here so I don't
trip over my own words I'm completely
obsessed with this topic and I've been
on it for a while now and that's because
the data are so robust and impressive
about what happen happens when you
optimize sleep performance so again I'm
not really talking about the
consequences of bad sleep on your
long-term health or things like that
it's the opposite it is how much of an
advantage you can create in your
performance when you sleep better one
quick example here because is something
we're dealing with right now with the
handful of our NFL athletes and that is
the ability to Aid in injury recovery
post surgery as well as even return to
play for concussion and other physical
problemss when we're maximizing sleep
but then there's also the direct
performance benefit uh pick your metric
here whether you want to look at
surrogates and physical attributes
things like endurance coordination speed
physical strength Etc you want to look
at onfield play so basketball shooting
accuracy tennis serving accuracy or
other markers of again performance
directly on the field but then probably
the one we use most often is it directly
translates into more wins and these data
are very well-rounded from a number of
areas the NFL the NBA the NHL the
Olympics PGA Tour etc etc there is clear
and impressive evidence that those who
maximize their sleep win more games now
I know what you're probably thinking
that's great Andy I'm sold I'm bought in
I want those benefits but it's just not
feasible for me to sleep more any number
of reasons whether you're an athlete or
not that could be legit and so I want to
make it Ultra clear here I'm not only
talking about the need to just extend
sleep and sleep more hours but how you
can mimic the benefits of sleep
extension for these performance
enhancement for these injury mitigation
and return to play benefits without just
extending the hours you sleep let me
give you a couple of examples here what
you may or may not realize is depending
on the study you pull somewhere between
20 to 40% of athletes have clinical
sleep disorders and so by simply
treating those things with any number of
simple and specific Solutions you can
create such improvements in Sleep
Quality
that you're effectively extending sleep
an easy example here for a major league
baseball player I worked with for a very
long time we had no reason to think he
had a sleep disorder slept pretty well
but not great kind of the same thing
you'll hear most people say I think I
sleep pretty well I'm not having huge
issues but I also don't feel incredible
either and so we are actually to get a
full appropriate diagnostic of him found
he was actually having a a large number
of sleep issues at night but the
solution is the fun part here we were
able to actually buy him a very cheap
pillow if you will it kind of looks like
a fanny pack that you wear in reverse
and that kept him from sleeping on his
back that reduced the amount of times he
woke up throughout the night by about
80% in the very first night and it
stayed that way ever since so again just
another example of the power of
precision and treating your sleep the
same way you would treat your training
and nutrition allowed us to create an
incredibly powerful sleep extension
solution with very minimal effort and it
didn't require us to change his daily
schedule ask him to get to bed much
earlier or any other things that are you
know sometimes not realistic uh for your
personal situation so for those reasons
and many many more I'm super pumped to
be talking about sleep performance today
now in doing that we're going to cover a
lot of the research both systematic
reviews meta analyses as well as direct
studies on this I've also talked to a
number of uh professional experts in
this field and so I'm going to be
bringing you a combination of what the
research says what these experts in the
field say what I've used in the athletes
I've worked with and my personal
experience and we're going to bring all
that together in a cohesive system to
help you do what we always do here and
that is address the three eyes so we'll
start off by investigate so how do you
investigate how do you measure and
diagnose and manage your sleep the
second eye being of course how do you
interpret that how do I know if that's
good great okay sufficient I'm good
enough or Etc and then three how do I
intervene so what do I do about it what
are protocols and approaches and
solutions we can take uh to solve any of
these individual problems as always
throughout that I'll try to cover the
landscape so we'll talk about cheap
solutions uh free Solutions what can we
do if I manage a team of people if it's
for me personally rather than people I'm
coaching all the way up to what are the
best in the world doing what are things
that are maybe within your financial
reach or not but what is the gold
standard in all of these things while
I'm going to be spending most of my time
talking about the research directly on
high performing athletes I do want to
remind you that it's not necessarily our
core interest here that you play sports
coach Sports participate orever want to
be involved in sports it's just that
that to me represents a great surrogate
for people that are trying to maximize
their total Human Performance whether
this is their physical performance
cognitive performance mental performance
or otherwise and so understanding this
gold standard of high performance allows
us to use some of the same skills and
tools and tactics for folks that are
also trying to ask the same out of their
individual body but perhaps not applying
it to sport so whether this is things
like Physicians night nurses military
folks judges anyone else who's really
trying to ask your body to perform at
the highest level possible now before we
go too much further I'd like to take a
quick break and thank our sponsors
because they make this show possible not
only are they on this list because they
offer great products and services but
because I actually personally love them
and use them myself today's episode has
brought to you by ag1 ag1 is a
foundational nutrition greens supplement
what's that mean it means that ag1
provides a comprehensive variety of
vitamins minerals probiotics prebiotics
and adaptogens in an easy to drink
greens powder getting your nutritional
right is hard for many people I
certainly know that I have clients who
really struggle for whatever reason to
get the proper nutrients from whole food
sources now ag1 is not a replacement for
eating high quality Whole Foods but it
is a great foundational supp for filling
in the gaps where needed I've also
personally found that with many of my
clients ag1 helps move them just in the
right direction for eating more
highquality Foods because it helps them
with Cravings digestion and many other
benefits I especially personally like
taking ag1 when I'm on vacation or
traveling because it helps me just sort
of stay on track with my nutrition I
know that missing a few days of getting
the proper vitamins and minerals and
other micronutrients is not a big deal
at all that's not really how those
things work but for me again I just like
knowing that I'm kind of staying
somewhat on track when I'm definitely
not making the best nutrition in food
choices of my life if you'd like to try
ag1 you can go to drink a1.com perform
to receive five free travel packs plus a
year supply of vitamin D3 plus G2 again
that's drink a1.com perform to receive
five free travel packs plus a year
supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 today's
episode is also brought to you by
element element is an electrolyte drink
mix that has an ideal ratio of sodium
potassium and magnesium but has no sugar
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration which I've been harping on for
years but you can't do that by only
drinking water in fact many of you will
probably remember that I featured
element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration all the way back in
2020 which is obviously long before this
podcast even existed so I've been a fan
of element for a long time in fact as
stent listeners will also realize these
hydration videos were the Genesis of the
Galpin hydration equation named not by
me but by the legendary neuroscientist
Dr Andrew hubman I featured element in
these videos because they're blend of
1,000 milligrams of sodium 200
milligrams potassium and 60 milligram
magnesium really is different than any
other electrolyte on the market and has
great scientific support however I want
to be ultra clear 1,000 Mig of sodium is
a lot and not everyone needs that much
in fact that may be way too much if you
don't exercise or sweat much already eat
a lot of salt in your diet say from a
lot of processed foods or otherwise have
sodium related medical concerns I
personally use the Citrus and watermelon
flavors a ton to preh hydrate before
heading out on a full day of training or
long hike or a hunt since I know I'll be
losing a bunch of fluids and won't have
many opportunities to take things with
me element has also just released a new
line of canned sparkling element which I
am all about if if you'd like to try
element you can go to drink LM
n.com perform to claim a free element
sample pack with the purchase of any
element drink mix again that's drink LM
nt.com perform to claim a free sample
pack now before we get started I need to
clarify a few things as always is the
case in science we need to make sure
that we're understanding the same words
we're operationally defining terms so
there's no confusion and so the first
one I want to talk about really here is
the difference between sleep deprivation
and extreme sleep restriction I've
mentioned that a second ago but just
really wanted to double down and clarify
that I'm not really going to be talking
about research the benefits what happens
to Performance when you go through
things like complete sleep deprivation
there's actually a lot of research on
that a lot from the military when you
take people and you have them go 24 or
48 hours without sleep and then you
return there's tons of evidence on what
happens to Performance in a lot of areas
but again I'm really not going to pay
attention to any of that stuff because
that's not what I'm getting at and I'm
also not talking about short-term
studies that use extreme sleep
restrictions so this is maybe two three
or four hours of sleep per night for the
course of 3 to 14 days those are
important things to do and they have a
lot of applications for a lot of
individuals but really I'm keeping most
of we're going to talk about exclusive
to the evidence behind again what
happens to this suboptimal sleep this is
defined typically as folks that are
trying to sleep normally um but maybe
only sleeping between six to maybe seven
and a half hours versus those that are
getting seven seven and a half up to
eight or nine okay so it would take us a
long time to get through that other
research and it is but sometimes it over
appreciates or can can conflate the
benefits or Consequences of bad sleep in
those special situations so just want to
make sure you're clear when you're
hearing the numbers and the evidence
behind what I'm going to talk about
later it's not coming from studies using
those types of examples and so what
we're really talking about here is
chronic suboptimal sleep and there's
three areas first one being duration so
we're talking about is how much time you
sleep second one being quality and as
you'll see later that is extraordinarily
difficult to get our heads around
there's no Universal definition there
and so we've got to have some uh
extensive conversation about what to do
about that and we absolutely will and
then third is timing and so there's a
lot that goes into timing of the day
Circa rhythms chronotypes and stuff like
that and so that's where we're going to
spend most of our time in our
conversation today if if you really want
I've got a handful of systematic reviews
in a number of areas that I think are
super effective all coming in the last
couple of years I've spoken with a
number of sleep professionals these are
phds MDS as well as on the grounds
practitioners of sleep and professional
sports coming from the NFL the NBA the
military Special Forces specifically
those dealing with the astronauts Etc
and they all have given me confidence
that these handful of articles are very
good so I feel strong in them I've read
them extensively those will all be in
the show notes available but just want
to read the title off of some of those
right now first one is sleep and the
athlete a narrative review and 2021
expert consensus recommendation um this
has got a large number of authors on
this if you're unfamiliar with a
consensus statement means it generally
refers to a number you know typically
five to 25 or more scientists in a given
area come together and say what are the
things we all agree upon and so they
tend to be very strong in confidence
because you know so many authors from
different institutions worked on this so
this paper I know um came from Neil
walls who's well-respected and
extensively published scientist in the
area as well as Amy Bender um whom I
spoke to directly about this and so this
is a great article to get you started on
that another is sleep hygiene for
optimizing recovery in athletes a review
and
recommendations again uh from another
strong group of scientists um at a UC
San Diego go um published in the last
couple of years and then the final one
is managing travel fatigue and jet lag
and athletes a review and consensus
statement um from 2021 so there are many
many many many other papers there but I
I chose those three specifically I
thought they were easy to read very
useful and can get you started in a lot
of the major areas and so that being
said we need to recognize a couple of
final things before we dive into the
details of this episode and that is this
field is honestly quite emerging people
have obviously been studying sleep for
many many decades but it's almost
exclusively from the perspective of you
know disease and overall health in fact
over 80% of the research on sleep and
athletes has been published in the last
decade alone we have other major
limitations a lot of it has come from
research on questionnaires so using
things like subjective analysis of your
sleep and they haven't necessarily
always been validated as uh quality in
athletes so another challenge there
research on females specifically is
exceptionally limited and so there is
some initial indication that the
requirements may be different for
females maybe not but we just really
honestly don't have enough information
there to make a firm conclusion so
something that needs to to be increased
in the future and then lastly it is
honestly challenging to control or blind
people in sleep studies you going to
know pretty quickly if you're in the
sleep for 10 hours per night group or in
the six hours per night group and so
that is a limitation in a number of the
studies we're going to cover but that is
always the case in science there's no
Panacea there's no perfect study so it's
always about evaluating the quality of
that study other studies in the field
from other Laboratories and then making
a consensus based on the information
that you do have so while the evidence
base here is more limited than we would
like there is enough there for the
authors of these papers as well as
honestly myself to conclude a couple of
things and the first is that athletes
need to be screened for Sleep Disorders
we'll talk about why that matters so
much and how to get it done a little bit
later the second is we have a huge
opportunity to create a competitive
Advantage by developing more precise and
effective sleep plans for our athletes
now this needs to be done based on
people's unique
physiology but even more broadly than
that can just be done from sport to
Sport and think about it this way the
reasons or the ways we can enhance sleep
in a football player are probably
different than those in a swimmer
because the challenges they face in
their schedule in their body size in the
demands energy expenditure are quite
different so giving them all the same
Solutions well hey it's better than
nothing but that lacks the Precision
we're looking for so in both those cases
we could create more effective sleep
extension by being more precise with
what we're asking them to do and
probably then have less Road Blocks less
problems with adherence and less overall
complaints from the athletes with that
you get more adherence you get more
success and we get more performance
benefits now I would love to tell you
I'm the first and only one who's on to
this secret area but that's not the
honest truth the research is growing the
emphasis of this in individual sports
and organizations is also growing in
fact I get asked all the time in
interviews what do I think kind of the
next big area of human performances and
sleep is often my number one or two
answer it's extremely clear uh there's a
really interesting paper that came out
recently by Dr Allison Breer called
Sleep is of the muscle by the muscle and
for the muscle and in that she called
Sleep the um easiest and cheapest way to
enhance a the health and performance and
I think Allison is dead on there if you
look at what's happened the
international Olympic Committee um the
NCAA have both came out with statements
in the last couple of years putting
sleep as fundamental to athlete health
and putting large emphasis on this we
see a growing number of sleep
performance special
popping up around at least in the United
States the University of Washington I
know has recently had every one of their
football players diagnosed for a sleep
disorder um I've been in conversation
with a number of professional sport
teams who are either trying to build
sleep performance programs hire
specialists in that area and to really
put the same emphasis on this that they
have their training and nutrition so
while it's not there yet it is clearly
something that behind the scenes is
being worked on in fact I would even say
that if you're not doing that you're
going to get left behind pretty quickly
uh because this is such a clear and
obvious win sleep affects nearly every
physiological process whether we're
talking about performance enhancement or
recovering from injury or concussion
it's also really really bad in so many
people I've mentioned that depending on
the study you look at somewhere between
20 to 40% of athletes have Sleep
disorders and then as I've teased a
couple of times the solutions to sleep
have traditionally just been like hey
yeah man sure that's great but try to
have my 19-year-old NBA player sleep
more good luck that's not where the
field is anymore the solutions that are
available are way more realistic and
effective than that and so as we
continue to see these people put a
greater emphasis on sleep I wanted to
make sure that that wasn't just
information hid behind the scenes to
some of these high performers that
everyone had access to the same tools
and tactics so as we start jumping into
the details now I want you to remember I
think about sleep in three major areas
the first is duration so hours or time
am amount you've spent sleeping second
is quality and third is timing so let's
get started with duration now I think
what's most interesting here is a field
of research called Sleep extension or
sleep banking this is the idea that you
will add on amount of time you're
sleeping so you're asking people to
increase the amount of time they are
sleeping from anywhere between 30 to up
minutes to up to two hours now this
always brings a smile to my face and
other people's when I talk about this
because they're like yeah sure I'm just
going to sleep two more hours yeah
you're going to and the reality of it is
the research on this shows that it is
quite effective you will again see
studies that have done this they'll ask
people to either do accommodation of
things they'll simply give them a time
and they'll say you know try to sleep
for 10 hours per night and so as a
result of that they'll increase their
sleep by an hour or two hours or
wherever they started with others
they'll actually just give a number so
try to sleep for 90 more minutes or 30
more minutes or something like that and
if you look at the results of most of
these studies you will see for the most
part these groups will increase the
amount of time that they sleep from you
know plus orus 30 minutes to up to 2
hours so it is very effective and
plausible where this all got started was
actually around the year 2000 um this
kind of study came out initially looking
at work in in cognitive function um
reaction time and mood and stuff like
that but this field really launched off
in 2008 with a seminal and classic study
that you know quote unquote shocked the
Sleep World from the Walter Reed
Institute this is a facility that does a
lot of research for the Army what they
found was effectively huge benefits and
people who went through sleep extension
prior to known sleep restriction and so
this is very interesting now the same
year Sher ma from Stanford came out with
the Classic basketball sleep extension
study if you're familiar with that and
this is really what set the field on
fire and there's been a ton of work
since that but I think it's such an
important paper that I want to go
through it in detail because effectively
what they did was found massive
improvements in sport ability so whether
you're talking about free throw shooting
percentage reaction time three-point
shooting percentage in the Stanford
basketball team so you're talking about
division one athletes that had 9%
improvements in shooting accuracy over
the course of a season by sleeping two
additional hours per night and so
there's a lot to unpack there how do you
get college kids to sleep two additional
hours per night and did you really say a
9% Improvement in free throw and
three-point shooting accuracy throughout
the course of his season yes yes yes and
plenty of things more so I want to go
through that paper a little more detail
because again I think it really
highlights the power of sleep extension
as a huge performance enhancing tool so
as I mentioned this was conducted at the
University of Stanford with their
division one basketball players and I
want to compliment Sherry and her team
having done research like this I know
how extraordinarily difficult it can be
there are of course limitations to get
you started right away there's no
control group here um we also don't know
how much of a benefit they had in their
performance just because of the course
of the season and a bunch of other
issues but doing research like this on
actual High performing athletes is like
next to Impossible this actually took
her several years to complete because of
just how difficult such a process would
be so um lots of limitations of course
but still lots of things we can glean
from this especially because it launched
the entire field in my opinion there are
other studies that have come out since
this both from Sherry's group and others
looking at um endurance cyclists
swimmers tennis players rugby players
and a bunch of other stuff so um yes
some limitations to this specific study
but let's really rather than worry about
the details and the numbers here just
just pay attention um to the thought and
the exercise of how much this stuff can
help so getting us started what they did
is they took the athletes and they were
able to get 11 of them to complete it
they had to screen out for anybody with
any sleep issues or use any drugs they
didn't allow alcohol or caffeine use the
entire time and they had them perform
their normal sleep for two to four weeks
or so now the reason it's two to four
weeks is you know because the challenges
of working with real athletes in real
time in real Sport Seasons as I
mentioned it took them a couple of
Seasons so not all the same participants
came from the same year of play um so
they were able to get folks in and just
depending on preseason scheduling
testing and other stuff like that the
the climatization period there um was a
little bit different so two to four
weeks the study itself lasted 5 to seven
weeks for those same reasons so they had
people sleep normally for two or four
weeks and then they ask them to sleep
for 10 hours per night again that
resulted in about a 2-hour sleep
extension on average some participants
had less some did more they had uh they
they tracked their sleep with a
combination of sleep logs so this is you
know just think about a notebook and the
athlete wrote down how long they slept
and quality of their sleep and things
like that as well as what's called
actigraphy you'll probably recognize
that as as wearables so think about a a
device on their wrist that measured
their sleep so not the gold standard
polygraphy of course but still a lot of
insightful stuff in the application of a
high performing athlete what was really
cool about this is they and kudos to the
coaches too they worked directly with
the sport coaches so they had a bunch of
physical performance testing so they did
one test that's called a 282 foot um
test so I think this is they ran from
Baseline to half court to back to
Baseline to the end of the full court
back to Baseline and they were timed on
that they had a bunch of other physical
performance metrics as well again as I
mentioned threo shooting uh free throw
shooting and I'll talk about those in a
second but they did those because those
were a part of their normal standard
testing anyway so they weren't asking
the participants to do anything
differently they weren't having them
come to the lab and do additional work
and why that I think is very important
is because getting an athlete to come to
your lab and do testing for a study in
season in in my experience I'll just
tell you again a little bit behind the
curtain here you're probably not going
to get a great effort and so when you
start looking for maximum results and
performance it really comes down to how
motivated the person was that day or not
but this was different this was in their
practice with their coaches so I I
promise you they were trying to shoot as
best they could not just in the post
testing but the preseason testing too
right like you want to make your team
you want to play more same thing with
their conditioning test so really strong
uh evidence there for the performance
benefits because they're trying to do
their best because that's what they're
you know coaches are asking them to test
there they also um did a combination
like I said of shooting I think they
shot 10 free throws um and I think they
shot 15 threep pointers and they kind of
took the you know how many did you make
out of 10 sort of thing
uh also this stuff was not done one time
this was a common performance test done
multiple times throughout the year and
so they're not just affected by hey was
it one bad day was that person sick or
hurt or had a bad night sleep the night
before or something like that so very
robust testing from that perspective
they took pycho motor testing as well um
this is actually a cool thumb tap test
so that this is something they could do
on their phone and it measures reaction
time and a bunch of other stuff uh where
a little thing will pop up on their
screen and they'll tap it with their
thumb kind of as fast as I can and so
they're getting this combination of
attention because it happens over a long
period of time um so how were they able
to focus or or did they lose track of
what they're doing and stop paying
attention as well as the reaction time
so pretty extensive and elaborate study
design that maximizes what we call
ecological validity um as well as
external validity so how would this
apply in the real world and this case
you know being able to pay more
attention and shooting better in
practice are are pretty strong standards
and metrics that people would care about
so what actually happened here I'm going
to walk you through the results in both
absolute and relative terms if you've
been involved or read much Human
Performance research you'll know both of
those metrics are actually important
when you're considering the context
whether or not this was you know
something to pay attention to or not
easy example here is you know sometimes
a 1% Improvement in performance may not
be enough to reach statistical
significance but it might be practically
relevant if this resulted in you say
jumping two inches higher
but it wasn't enough you know again to
reach stat Sig here but most
practitioners would care about 2 Ines so
let me walk you through both so you have
the most appropriate accurate
information and then you can judge
yourself whether or not you you feel
like this is worthy of note or not so as
I mentioned they did the
282 foot Sprint test that's that you
know half court and back Etc test at
Baseline it took them about 16.2 seconds
to complete and at the end of sleep
extension it was down to 15.5 so reduced
that time by 7 seconds again I'll leave
that up to you to decide but to me
that's a pretty impressive Improvement
throughout the course of a season free
throw shooting percentage again this was
out of 10 and remember this is not just
one test pre one test post this was done
routinely throughout the season and then
you're getting an aggregate score here
so on average they made 7.9 shots out of
10 so you're call it an 80% free throw
percentage which be expected for
athletes at this high quality in a in a
practice situation and they were up to
8.8 or almost 90% this is the lot you're
effectively making one more free throw
out of 10 this is huge um and definitely
the difference between winning and
losing making a team playing Etc
three-point percentage was a similar
story so again these are out of 15 shots
so preseason they were making about 10
out of 15 60 percentage and all the way
up to 11.6 so you know added one to one
and a half extra makes per 15 attempts
again a really important both
statistically sign significant
Improvement as well as practically
important Improvement other metrics that
were included that were cool um
subjective rating at practice improved
scale of 1 to 10 here kind of seven out
of 10 before all the way up to almost
nine out of 10 at the end um same thing
with their subjective rating at games
7.8 out of 10 all the way up to 8.8 out
of 10 so lots of improvements and actual
performance and perception of
performance and then not going to run
you through all of the other metrics in
the study but you're going to see a
similar theme um with weekly reaction
time um daily morning reaction time of
this PBT tests I talked about um daily
evening stuff etc etc etc so not
everything came up as statistically
significant but most of it did and all
of it was a pretty similar magnitude so
it really just kind of looks like this
you know call it 3 to 10% Improvement in
most variables measured so I don't know
about you but if you walked into any
performance staff or coaches office or
walked into an athletes locker and said
I'm going to get you a 10% Improvement
in all these metrics throughout the year
I think you're going to catch their
attention so this stuff has certainly
caught mine now if this seems a little
bit too good to be true I'll be honest I
had the same feelings right when you
look at some of those numbers it's like
well that's a lot and you look at the
study and you're like hey there's no
control group and etc etc and so I said
man how do I think about this I started
calling friends colleagues of mine I
called Jeffrey durmer who's worked at
the Atlanta Falcons and USA
weightlifting and tons of other
professional sports I called Amy Bender
PhD and and sleep science and worked
with tons of professional athletes and
they basically all said the same thing
okay great let's say the results are
slightly exaggerated let's say they're
exaggerated by 25% let's say they're
exaggerated by 50% wouldn't you still
take a 5%
Improvement I would and those metrics in
that level of athlete where the margin
for improvement is so small anyways call
it 75%
exaggerated that's still a pretty big
impact and so when you compare that also
with the research in the same area um
you're talking about studies that have
been done of course that one in
basketball players but similar work from
Sherry's lab uh in swimmers um similar
thing as I mentioned in rugby players
and you're all going to find this kind
of global you know two to four to up to
10% Improvement in performance depending
on how you want to look at it um these
sleep extension studies r range from
three nights of sleep extension all the
way up to 7 weeks and it seems to me as
the evidence continues to grow you're
just seeing the same thing played out
more and more so while again the
specifics of can I guarantee you
sleeping two more hours improves your um
you know Ser tennis serving accuracy by
10% no I can't but am I confident it's
going to improve your
performance absolutely just to give a
little more context about the Sleep
extension research and athletes a couple
of other studies worth noting one of
them looked at an additional 1.7 hours
of sleep per night over the course of a
week and this was done in tennis players
and they found that it improved tennis
serving accuracy by about 6% or so
another one looked at a little bit less
so 45 minutes of extra sleep per night
but for a longer duration this was now 3
weeks and they found a Improvement in
Reaction Time by 4% as well as a
reduction in cortisol by 19% this was in
rugby players so a little bit different
demand a little bit different test but
still are similar story and the final
one of note was more similar to the
basketball study in which they asked him
to sleep for an hour and a half extra
per night but just for three total days
and so they their sleep time actually
went from about 7.1 hours per night to
almost 8.6 hours this is another example
of I'm not talking about going from four
hours of sleep tonight to 6 hours of
sleeper now we're talking people already
sleeping a decent amount 7 hours and
pushing them all the way up to close to
9 hours in this particular study they
found a 3% Improvement um in time trial
performance this is a 60-minute cycling
test um in these highly trained
endurance cyclists and athletes so again
wanted to share all of those studies
because it highlights it's not really
specific to basketball it's not just
physiology of endurance it's not just
skill it is really robust in terms of
how much it improves what areas of
performance improve how long you need to
do it for how much you need to sleep for
and so I don't want you to get too up in
either the numbers in terms of the
percentages of the improvements or even
really the protocol how many more
minutes for how long I think the take on
point is if you can get people to start
sleeping longer for a couple of days or
even for a couple of weeks and if longer
means 45 minutes or 2 hours it doesn't
really matter if you can get that stuff
you're going to see performance
improvements regardless I'd like to take
a quick break and thank our sponsors
today's episode is brought to you by
absolute rest sleep is the Bedrock of
human performance which is why I always
focus on it with my Elite athletes but
despite trying every wearable and even
sending people to full-blown clinical
testing in sleep Labs we rarely got very
far that's why two years ago I
co-founded absolute rest which redefines
what it means to be a high performance
sleeper after tremendous success we are
now ready for our next challenge a
firstof its kind sleep optimization
program that combines Advanced sleep
technology with personalized coaching
all at a fraction of the cost of a
traditional sleep study the Sleep lens
program allows you to run a full FDA
approved clinical grade sleep study from
your fingertip every single night our
team of sleep scientists then use your
data to create personalized solutions
that drive real changes in your sleep no
more overnight stays in creepy sleep
Labs no more wearables with questionable
accuracy and no more wondering if the
changes you're making in your nightly
routine habits or supplements are
actually working or not if you'd like to
try absolute rest go to Absolut rest.com
/ perform to secure your spot in the
Sleep lens program and save $100 that's
Absolut rest.com perform today's episode
is also brought to you by momentus
momentus makes supplements of the
absolute highest quality because in my
opinion no one is even close to their
quality and safety standards and they've
got the data to prove it for example
we've long known about the numerous
health and performance benefits of fish
oil I've personally been taking it for
probably 15 years or more numerous
Studies have consistently demonstrated
positive impacts of EPA and DHA the two
primary fish oils on everything from
cardiovascular and brain health to
exercise performance and joint pain now
you can get fish oil anywhere but
personally I only use momentus because
it's never once given me a fishy
aftertaste and more importantly every
single batch is NSF tested to ensure the
lead and mercury levels are undetectable
for Purity and saf safety their fish oil
is pure potent and sustainably sourced
another major benefit to their fish oil
and you can check the record here
because I've been talking about this in
my slides in class for over a decade is
that you won't find any fillers in their
fish soil see the dirty secret in the
industry here is that most companies
will add non-epa and dhas to their fish
oil to keep their quote fish oil count
high but to keep the active ingredients
and therefore costs low it makes you
actually feel like when you're
purchasing it you're getting more fish
oil at a cheaper price but you actually
have to double or triple your dose to
get the same amount of active ingredient
which means you end up spending more
money in the long run or you don't and
you get worse results if you want to
give their fish oil a shot or any other
momentus product go to Liv mous.com
perform to get 20% off your order again
that's Liv mous.com perform to get 20%
off now one more thing I wanted to pass
along to you that I thought was actually
pretty interesting regarding sleep
extension and you're not going to find
this in the peer-reviewed research this
is an anecdote to be totally caned with
you but still really important I I
talked actually at length with Dr
Jeffrey durmer who's an mdphd in sleep
it's been around for decades one of the
most profound and prolific sleep
scientists really of our time and he did
a lot of work in the NFL and he told me
that I'll have to say this as like
carefully as I can hear but he basically
said when working with one particular
NFL team that he noticed there was
wasn't really a huge Improvement in
performance or cognitive function or
reaction time that they could really
tell but the Sleep extension was
incredibly powerful at helping people
return from injuries uh the performance
staff felt it was very clear that there
guys were either getting hurt less often
but more specifically coming back from
those injuries faster than they were in
the Years prior to not paying attention
to sleep so again a number of potential
benefits here and rationale to exploring
this idea of extending your sleep
but I know what you're probably thinking
okay how do I do that number one and
then what if it's just not possible you
have got various sleep restrictions now
in this particular case I'm talking
about athletes as well as everybody else
so sometimes people don't realize
athletes want to sleep more but they
don't have the option to they've got
schedules they've got practices they've
got flights and travel and they've got
the same restrictions that the rest of
us have so again as I've mentioned I
really feel like the benefits of sleep
extension are quite profound the biggest
ISS though was really of practicality
and what I mean by that is you're
probably thinking dude I'm sold I'm in I
want to sleep more it's just not
possible whether you're an athlete or
non-athlete all of us have restrictions
on our time you may have other
obligations you may not and you just
can't sleep any longer throughout the
night or have any number of reasons so
what do we do if we believe in sleep
extension we want to get these
performance enhancement benefits out of
it but we just are not able to sleep for
more time for whatever reason well you
got a number of different options here
the very first is being more specific
and intentional about when you're trying
to extend your sleep the reality of it
is almost nobody has the ability to
sleep for nine or 10 hours a night every
day every night the entire year that's
an unrealistic expectations you're
setting yourself up to fail just like
you wouldn't do that with your nutrition
you wouldn't do that with your training
you wouldn't just run as many miles as
you can in a week you wouldn't lift as
many reps as you can you would have a
periodized approach so go through
periods where you're going for more
volume because you're going for Less
volume volum in other periods you're
going to have more calories during this
phase and less calories during other
phases I would say the same thing with
sleep extension and so think about your
schedule whether you've got an important
travel coming up you've got um a really
tight business schedule you've got work
obligations um we have a training camp
so we're starting preseason training um
we're in fight camp for MMA fighters we
have some other area of time that is
most important to us or is a time of
known sleep loss
right in that we probably want to go be
in front of that and get our what's
called Sleep banking in and so we're
going to look and say all right great
I'm going to remove things in my life if
I can or add things in my life like
napping or other things that allow me to
get towards that sleep extension in the
say 3 to 30 days prior to those those
big known losses of sleep a really good
example of this that I wish I had known
about but honestly didn't a number of
years ago I was fortunate to travel with
a UFC fighter named Brian Ortega that
I've worked with for many years and we
actually were able to go to Abu Dhabi
and fight at a place called fight Island
so this is really interesting this was
during the covid pandemic and the world
is basically shut down and the only
fighting and really the only sport
happening was the UFC in this specific
fight bubble out in Abu Dhabi now the
challenge with that is I live and Brian
live lives in Southern California and we
had to go all the way out to Abu Dhabi
so we had time change to deal with we
had travel to deal with and at the same
time we've got a very extensive weight
cut so Brian has to lose a decent amount
of weight like every fighter does
Brian's pretty normal in that area but
he's got a decent amount of weight to
lose in the four to five days prior to
um that performance in addition to that
we have to fight then a five round fight
we have just a number of media
obligations Brian is the headline event
so there's just a lot of challenges that
go into this so we've got to go over
there and we got to try to manage one of
the key variables which is sleep when we
get over there
and we've got to now also deal with the
fact that we have to fight not at local
time but because the UFC is an American
company for the most part they generally
want their fights to happen during
American prime time so I think we end up
fighting if I remember correctly
something like 6 a.m. local time in the
morning so that it could be at you know
700 p.m. p.m. PST you know in California
or whatnot and so we went over there
with the idea of saying okay great and I
timed everything out I pre uh prepared I
used an app called called time shifter
um to help make sure all of our circad
rhythms were on the right point and
everything was plotted out weeks in
advance and I thought we had a perfect
system there unfortunately what I didn't
realize is when we got there all of
Brian's media obligations were still at
Abu Dhabi local time so this was right
in the middle of our sleep window so we
tried to stay on California time but
he's been woken up all day to do press
conferences and weigh-ins and media and
things like that and so it end up being
an entire sleep disaster he got almost
No Sleep uh I I probably had one night
of straight sleep the
entire almost two weeks we were there
just disrupted uh his body was all over
the place every metric we had was just
off the charts gone cuckoo he had no
idea when he was awake or sleeping it
was a really really challenging thing we
were fortunate Brian actually went on to
perform had one of his best performances
ever and won the fight we got to come
home but it was an absolute disaster
looking back on that there wasn't much I
could do right he had to perform at that
time
he was going to have to do the media
obligations there's just nothing we
could do about it the only real solution
I would have had was to bank his sleep
prior to going out there it would he
would not have performed at his best no
question the research um especially from
the military is really clear here when
you go through no now we're talking
really known sleep uh
restriction sleep deprivation which is
where we were at if you if you go
through sleep extension prior to events
like that you can um you can blunt or
attenuate the drop in performance which
is to say the performance drop will
happen but you can have it go down
slower if you Bank some sleep going into
it so I wish I would have known about
that I didn't um this was again many
years ago and I just didn't know that
information so would have gone back next
time if we have have to go through
something like that we're absolutely
going to bank probably at least three
weeks prior to um as much as we can of
course we're trying to sleep as much as
we can being in fight Camp regardless
but we would have made other changes to
ensure he had access to more sleep
because we knew we were going to have
such a challenge over there so didn't
know it at the time we were in a unique
situation lesson learned but a key tool
and tactic I will certainly use in my
coaching practice for the rest of my
career so why is it sleep extension is
such a powerful performance-enhancing
tool well it's because of what I call
the athlete sleep Paradox and that is
despite what you may think athletes tend
to sleep less and worse than
non-athletes despite the fact that they
probably actually need more sleep and so
you can look at this from a lot of
different ways um there's been a number
of longitudinal studies done on divers
and rowers and skiers and cyclists and
what you're going to kind of
collectively find is most athletes tend
to sleep in the neighborhood of six and
a half to seven hours per night now the
average person is in that range you know
maybe in the seven hours or so and so
you can see the athletes are a little
bit lower but they actually need even
more you can Sher ma actually from
Stanford the Sleep extension study also
published another paper and in that she
looked at 620 athletes at Stanford
across 29 different sports and found
that almost 40% of those athletes
reported sleeping less than 7 hours per
night during the weekdays and over 50%
reported extremely high daytime
sleepiness and so again you can chop
this up and look at all the different
papers but you're going to find a
similar note athletes tend to sleep
worse and there's a lot of reasons for
this some of it's very practical they
have early morning practices they have
extensive late night games or
competitions some of it is because of
physical nature athletes tend to be
bigger than other people and so their
necks are larger and this alone can be
um a predictor or cause of sleep
disorders um they tend to have worry and
anxiety the night before sport
competitions and things like that um
depending on what sport th they may have
caloric restriction or other um
excessive training just a lot of other
things that go into it and so some of it
is behavioral some of it is lifestyle
some of it is physiology and some of it
is is just the nature of what they go
into in terms of competing and so
they're in this really hard spot they
need more sleep arguably than other
folks and yet they're sleeping actually
less so puts them in a really big bind
so it's really no surprising when even
if they're sleeping at 7 hours and we
take them to nine we see these giant
bumps in performance it's almost like
you know minimally or lowly active
individuals going from 6 hours a night
to eight and a half right because
they're almost in a little bit of a
pseudo sleep debt because they're simply
not matching the demand what they need
let alone going all the way up to the
top to maximize recovery and performance
and as I mentioned this is really not
extreme sleep restriction so there's a
lot of really cool papers and the line
seems to be somewhere in this like seven
to 7 and a half hours range there is a
significant difference in in all things
um that there was one study looking at
getting a cold or being sick and found
that an additional 30 minutes a night uh
increased or decreased rather your
chance of getting a cold by fourfold
right so huge in performance there
there's a really cool paper on tweeting
I guess we'll call it Xing now but
tweeting in NBA players and all they did
was look at just publicly available
tweets on NBA players and looked at how
late they were tweeting at night
postgame and found there was a
1.7% Improvement in shooting accuracy
and those who are not up tweeting late
at night and so just that alone like a
really low quality indicator of sleep
you know how much you Tweeting at night
was explained almost 2% of shooting
accuracy again you take any NBA coach
you take any basketball coach and say we
can give you 2% bump in shooting
accuracy this is a really big number
especially in a high performer who
doesn't have much room to go um again
rugby similar thing right there was a
really cool study looking at rugby in
kind of a three-week preseason training
phase and they found both body
composition and aerobic performance were
significantly better in those athletes
who slept more than 7 and 1 half hours
relative to those who slept less Les
than S and a half hours right and then
finally U there there's been a number of
studies kind of on injury and then the
line there is again you go from s hours
to sleep at night to eight hours of
sleep per night and then this one study
in particular U found that that
increased injury Risk by 1.7 fold so
again there's lots of examples I can
come up with here but there is just a
lot of information suggesting it really
is not the same sleeping 7 and 1/2 hours
or 7 hours is like okay I feel fine I
feel normal or I'm a little bit sleepy
but it's not that big a deal would 30
more minutes really matter would an hour
really matter and hopefully I'm
convincing you that yeah yeah it does it
matters a lot so I could keep going here
and share with you more research but I
think you're getting the point generally
athletes are not sleeping enough for
their demands what actually is I think
really interesting is this sets up this
athlete sleep Paradox I talked about a
second ago and that is athletes don't
sleep enough even though they actually
probably need more that second part
though is a little bit more confusing
why athletes need more sleep there's not
a strong relationship at least
scientifically that we know of yet
between energy expenditure say calories
or you know how much work you put in and
minutes needed per sleep it doesn't seem
to work like that so you can't simply
say I ran a few more miles today or I
was a little more active my steps were
higher therefore I need x amount of
minutes per sleep or maybe you do but
you actually won't sleep that much more
so there isn't a tight relationship
there clearly seems to be some
relationship between energy output and
SL some sleep but again it's not a
onetoone relationship and so when I talk
to a lot of the people in this area I
kind of pressed them on that and there's
a couple of different reasons one of
them is those studies really just
haven't been done and they haven't been
done in high performers so there may
actually be that relationship there may
not we don't know that's an omission of
the research at this point but there's
actually enough bi chemistry here for
you us to Inuit it that there's probably
something happening here and so a couple
of things to think about one we're not
talking about returning to Baseline
we're talking about people who are
trying to create new adaptation so it is
not just recovering it is now optimizing
or maximizing so that's one the second
thing is think about what we're asking
athletes to do so let's remember some
basic or let's learn some basic
biochemistry of exercise here now
everything in biology uses a single
molecule for energy called ATP stands
for adenosine triphosphate so it is an
adenosine molecule with three that's why
it's called Tri phosphates attach to
each other it doesn't matter where
you're getting the energy from to create
that ATP fats proteins carbohydrates
doesn't matter what animal you're in
frankly or what you're using the energy
for digestion exercise recovery brain
function it's irrelevant it's all using
that magic energy currency called ATP
all right now the way that this operates
is there are high energy bonds that
connect one of the phosphates to the
second phosphate to the third phosphate
so you can kind of think of this Iden in
the middle and this little tail of the
three phosphates when you break off one
of those phosphates from the other you
end up with a molecule that is not
adenine triphosphate is adenine D
phosphate because it now has two
phosphates and then you have that third
phosphate is what we call an an organic
free floating phosphate okay now by
breaking that phosphate off you broke
that bond that has a net release of
energy you put some energy into the
system to break the bond but it gave out
more energy after it broke than it did
to break it and so that's an exonic
reaction you've generated energy use
that energy to you know power your
exercise or recovery or whatever you're
doing so as a net result of that every
time you've asked your your body for
energy you have created an ADP and that
phosphate okay the fate of the phosphate
we'll talk about in another episode or
conversation if you were to ask yourself
for more energy or ask your body for
more energy rather you would break that
ADP again so you snap that second
phosphate off and you would turn it into
a Denine mono phosphate at so one of
them you do it one more time now that
third phosphate is gone and you just
simply have a Denine well why does that
matter a Denine is a little molecule
that binds to little Lian receptors all
throughout your body particularly in
your brain and this controls fatigue or
rather sleepiness and so what happens
and this in fact this is exactly how
caffeine works right so adenosine or
caffeine rather competitively binds to
those adenosine receptors and so that it
blocks the perception of fatigue so when
more adenosine accumulates throughout
the body on those receptors more
sleepiness more fatigue and so
throughout the day as you're going
through metabolism you're creating
you're generating more energy you're
creating more free amounts of adenosine
more of it is binding to those receptors
and you're increasing what's called your
sleep pressure so you're sleeping a and
fatigue is building over time and this
is great when you sleep at night you
remove those adenosines you recycle them
create them back into ATP and so you've
recycled your energy your sleepiness
goes away your grogin goes away and your
energy comes back up the next day this
is our sleep wake cycle right when you
wake up the next morning that feeling of
grogginess that feeling of sleepiness is
called Sleep inertia this is getting up
in the morning right this is related to
how much adenosine you've effectively
cleared throughout the night this is one
of the many many reasons why sleeping
better at night or sleeping more
effectively sleeping more allows you to
feel less groggy the next day sleeping
of a higher quality Etc it's also why as
I'll talk about in a little bit bit
things that people tend to think are
normal with their sleep are not so it is
not common to feel groggy all day it is
not common um to be able to sleep kind
of on command throughout the day those
are strong signs that you are probably
not clearing all the adenosine um there
could be other things going on but that
could be one of the things that's
happening it is still left there it's
why you also potentially don't have as
much energy the next day because you
don't have the adenosine to make enough
HP that becomes a problem so where
caffeine enters the picture is caffeine
competitively binds to the same
receptors so when it is stuck onto that
receptor the adenosine can't bind there
so you don't get that same sense of
fatigue and so that's why uh it caffeine
has both a stimulation effect as well as
an anti- fatigue effect so there it's
also again why if caffeine is consumed
too late or not metabolized uh
sufficiently enough that you're going to
have a hard time sleeping at night
because you're not getting that same
adenosine binding not getting that same
um signal for sleepiness so it would
then make sense and we could Intuit it
someone who's going through more ATP
Recycling and production throughout the
day like an athlete like somebody who's
more um Physically Active would need
more sleep more time for the lymphatic
system to operate um more time to clear
um our overall adenosine now again we do
not have direct studies of this but the
intuition says this this makes sense
there have been some studies looking at
things like endurance athletes versus
other um say strength and power athletes
and it initially suggests that the
amount of time um during the sleep
stages were were particularly effective
um at clearing this stuff is enhanced
and so that's again another indirect
information and so I think at this point
there's enough for us to say all right
we can um we can turn the mechanism when
we don't have direct human trial
evidence then this is an appropriate
time to look at mechanism since we don't
have those trials for energy expenditure
and and high athletes and sleep duration
we can look at the mechanism and the
mechanism makes sense it makes
theological sense um it makes intuition
sense we have some other similar studies
like with the endurance athletes and so
you kind of combine that story on top of
the evidence that we know that athletes
still don't sleep enough as normal
people um or even less than and it makes
sense for us to say okay you need to
sleep more and you're probably not
sleeping enough as it is and you
probably have an argument for needing
more sleep than everyone else anyways
I'd like to take a quick break and thank
our sponsors today's episode is brought
to you by eight sleep eight sleep makes
Smart mattress covers with cooling
heating sleep tracking and more I've had
one for years and it is glorious I even
put one on the bed in my guest bedroom
because as you'll hear me talk about
endlessly here on the perform podcast
there really is nothing you can do that
makes a larger impact on your health and
performance than getting tremendous
sleep the eight sleep is a GameChanger
because I run hot or as my wife calls it
I'm a furnace and that's particularly
driven by the fact that I often have to
do my exercise training in the evenings
which is honestly not always great for
sleep but this is also the case of many
of the athletes that I work with who
don't have a choice when they compete
and so being able to cool down
immediately in bed does wonders for both
sleep latency and Sleep Quality eight
sleep recently launched their newest
generation of the Pod cover the Pod 4
ultra the Pod 4 ultra has two times more
cooling power yet is virtually silent
and even has snoring detection that will
automatic Ally lift your head in a few
degrees to improve the air flow and stop
you from snoring go to 8sleep.com
perform to save $350 off their pod 4
ultra eight sleep currently ships to the
USA Canada UK and select countries in
the EU and Australia again that's
8sleep.com
perform let's move on now and talk about
Sleep Quality now as I mentioned this is
very challenging because there is no
specific set definition for what quality
means in fact scientists argue about
this stuff constantly so as we go
through this research keep that in mind
I also want you to keep in mind that not
all Studies have used the same
methodology some have used what's the
gold standard so polygraphy actual test
where they hook up electrodes to
athletes and you know clinically
diagnose them and others have used
things like questionnaires that have
been scientifically validated but they
probably result in a higher percentage
of diagnosed disorders than the direct
test but nonetheless I'm just going to
give you some ballpark number here based
on the collective amount of research
right so if you look across the studies
that have been done on uh division one
football players the NFL uh the NHL
Olympic athletes rugby and things like
that you're going to see the number um
at 20 to 40% or so meaning that
percentage of athletes have clinically
diagnosed Sleep Disorders but what's
crazy is over 80% of those will go
undiagnosed and that's the same in the
general population so the overwhelming
majority of sleep disorders are never
actually known are identified and then
of course because of that um they're not
solved which is a huge problem in terms
of which disorders are most prevalent
You've Really Got The Big Three that is
obstructive sleep apnea um you have
insomnia and then the third one is
restless leg syndrome how much of these
exist in each well in Osa or sleep apnea
is pretty common most common 10 to 20%
probably has a lot to do with physical
size of athletes um but can be around
quite often insomnia is the second most
common and that's somewhere between four
and 12% of athletes will exhibit signs
at some point in their life of insomnia
um this is you know particularly
problematic in sports like wrestling and
swimming who utilize a combination of
late night or afternoon or evening
training sessions as well as very early
workouts so 4 5 600 a.m. workouts Um
this can either exacerbate insomnia
symptoms for those that have it or in
some cases unfortunately create it we'll
talk about solution steps for that a
little bit later restless leg syndrome
is also somewhat common you know
somewhere between 4 and
133% so another one um to keep up for
this is why in many other the consensus
statements you will see people
advocating for athletes to get tested at
least once a year for Sleep Disorders
because this is a really high number uh
let's even say that some of this is a
little bit exaggerated it's not 40% but
it is 25% that still means once one on
every four or five people um in your
room on your team in your locker room
has a clinical sleep disorder and almost
surely again 80% likely they're never
going to know about it so we're leaving
a lot of health and performance on the
table by not addressing our Sleep
Quality and addressing most specifically
Sleep Disorders again no specific
definition exists for Sleep Quality but
there's a lot of metrics that people
will use to infer that um some of the
things that jump out are efficiency so
this is like what percentage of time you
spend sleeping at night versus awake
another one called wazo wake after sleep
onset is a very common one there's
latency how long it takes you to fall
asleep and then fragmentation and you
look at the research on all those and
these globally tend to be worse in
athletes so you may or may not qualify
for a clinical Sleep Diagnosis but
that's not really what we're concerned
with right so the analogy here would be
an X-Ray so your knee hurts you go in to
the doctor they take an x-ray and they
say well it's not broken therefore it
must be optimal that that's not how it
works I'm still in pain I'm sub
suboptimal right so there's a difference
between getting a clinical di agnosis or
meeting a threshold for sleep disorder
and still having very poor or low
quality sleep so one actual study I'm
thinking of is colleague of mine Corey
peacock did this and this was cool
because this was in UFC fighters he
tracked them for an entire I think it
was somewhere between like a six to
eight week camp for a actual UFC fight
and they found that sleep latency was
one of the telltale signs of problems
and so this continued to get worse um
throughout the camps and it was actually
directly related to a number of
performance metrics so their sleep
latency was negatively correlated to V2
max heart rate recovery vertical jump
height and then what's probably most
important which is the amount of
workouts or training sessions that they
missed and these correlations were
strong all of these were about 08 or
higher one is the highest you possibly
get and so that alone is a phenomenal
thing to take a look at and and pay
attention to as a way to identify are I
sleeping at the highest quality maybe or
maybe not clinical disorder level so in
addition to sleep duration and quality
another lever we can press to enhance
performance is sleep timing now this is
actually really cool a lot of people
think about this simply as the context
of jet lag but it is more than that
there is circadian rhythms that you
perform the best in and it tends to be
your local time tends to be your
afternoon and so if you're traveling and
you're changing time zones this matters
but if you're also manipulating when
you're performing
even within your time zone it can mimic
the same effect so what I'm getting at
here is if you can optimize timing you
can get the benefits of sleep extension
and improving Sleep Quality without
changing either of them and what I mean
by this is the the the research is so
cool here because it comes directly from
games one there's a lot of research U
across a bunch of different sports the
NBA the NFL Major League Baseball the
NHL there's a bunch of studies going
back um through 10 years 30 years up to
40 Years of historical games and they
look at these things and they say okay
can we predict who's going to win more
games based simply on a combination of
are they playing in their right
circadian time or not so the example
here would be let's imagine you have a
West Coast team and they're normally
used to competing at 400 p.m. on the
west coast and they travel to the
Midwest or the East Coast but they
compete at a time that is still 4:00 on
the West Coast time so it's their normal
circadian rhythm they have a big
advantage over the other team because
they're playing in their normal Rhythm
despite the fact that they've changed
time zones so it's more complicated and
more interesting than just you know jet
lag which is obviously very very
important so this Rhythm um this there's
a ton of information here Steven lley
from Harvard uh he's been around for
forever published a ton in this area was
Monumental in developing the Circadian
rhythm and light timing um for the
International Space Station um he has a
great app I have no affiliation to this
but it's called time shifter which helps
you set your your supplementation and
light and food stuff for if you're
traveling internationally I've used it
for years I've paid full price for it
lots of stuff there but he's done a ton
of research on this stuff and it's
really compelling so Steve has done so
much cool work in this area but I'm
going to condense it to just hit a
couple of points um one study I think of
in particular was they they went back
and looked at performance in Olympic
swimming from 2004 to 2016 and they were
able to predict 3% of Performance Based
simply on on circadian timing right so
again we're not talking about who slept
more or who had Sleep Disorders or
anything is simply can you play and
perform in the right time for your body
I think more interesting is Sher ma from
Stanford who I've mentioned before um
spent I think about three years working
with ESPN and what she was able to do is
predict somewhere between the
neighborhood of 70 to 80% accuracy of
who would win NFL games based simply on
the team's time zone so this is this is
incredible obviously this is stuff that
people use in um those in the sports
betting worlds behind the scenes a lot
part of the information if you ever
wonder why a betting line is where it is
on some teams this is a huge component
to that certainly not the only one but
it's really cool stuff so um again be
able to understand and enhance your
performance if sleep extension is out of
the question if sleep diagnostic is out
of the question if Sleep Quality you're
trying and it's not working whatever
another way again you can get yourself
to per huge performance enhancements is
manipula
your timing the more you can stay
consistent and performing in your own
local space whenever you used to
performing the better you're going to be
let me give you one tangible example so
you have something to lock on to here
the University of Washington football
team my hometown team candidly is going
to be dealing with the unique challenge
they are right now in the Pack 12 which
means every team they play is on the
west coast they're moving to a division
that is in the midwest so they're going
to be playing Ohio and Pennsylvania and
Iowa and Minnesota and things like that
so let's imagine this let's imagine the
University of Washington typically
played their football games as they do
either at 4:30 p.m. or 7:30 p.m.
Washington time okay great so if they
played a team at 4:30 at home and that
team came from the East Coast or Midwest
University of Washington has an
advantage the other team traveled and
now they're competing at their normal
local time huge win for the University
of Washington but another scenario gets
more interesting let's imagine that
they're on the road and let's imagine
they went to Ohio State as an example
and they played that game at 7:30 p.m.
Eastern time zone now this is actually
still despite the fact that they're on
the road this is still a huge Advantage
for the University Washington because
7:30 East Coast time is still 4:30 West
Coast time so not only is the University
of Washington competing on their normal
circadian rhythm but Ohio State in this
case is competing at a way delayed
Rhythm um typically those teams are
going to be playing at about noon local
time so instead of playing at noon local
time they're now playing at 7:30 local
time they've shifted their performance
window 7 and a half hours so in this
particular case despite the fact we
would be on the road we'd have a
three-hour time zone difference there
would still be a slight 1 to 2% uh
Advantage for the University of
Washington third example here would be
the opposite let's imagine again
University of Washington typically plays
at 4:30 p.m. Seattle time and they go to
Columbus or Ohio State and they play a
game at Columbus or Ohio's normal time
which is noon Eastern Time right this is
now 9 o'l in the morning for the
University of Washington this is now
many what are we uh almost eight hours
earlier than normal would be a massive
Advantage not only because the time
shift change the travel being on the
road but because the circadian rhythms
um you would probably be looking at you
know maybe a four to five to six%
Advantage just on that fact alone to the
Ohio State team so something to really
pay attention to those of you that have
the opportunity or ability to manipulate
this I would encourage you to do so but
something again we can really pay
attention to when sleep extension or
Sleep Quality are not on the table as
variables that we can improve it's now
time for us to really get into the
details of the three eyes the first eye
being investigate which is how do I
assess and analyze my sleep the second
being interpret so how do I know whether
that's good bad great terrible or
otherwise and then third being intervene
so what do I do about it what protocols
and solutions do I have to solve these
problems so we'll start with the first
one and that's investigate now the
consensus article I talked about at the
very beginning of the show here has a
really nice model at the end to kind of
walk you through the steps so the way to
think about this is I'm probably not
going to be able to send every person I
know or even myself go to a sleep lab
and get a a full sleep study done you
know every month or every week or even
every year and so how do I actually use
a combination of free to maybe moderate
Le to all full-blown sleep studies and
how do I decide who to use that and so
they have a really nice uh overall
testing model that we'll do now to me
this is really important because I've
talked to you already about uh how
prevalent Sleep Disorders are the other
thing I haven't mentioned yet though is
is how bad people are at assessing their
own sleep you can look at any number of
Publications here but specifically those
on athletes show that they are
notoriously bad at estimating both their
Sleep Quality their sleep quantity um
how long it took them to fall asleep as
well as and this is one that matters how
much it's actually affecting their
cognitive and physical performance
colleague of mine Ian denkin has done a
number of studies in this area and it is
mind-blowing how bad athletes are at
this and we actually just recently
completed a paper together where we uh
assessed sleep and nutrition and
training in combat sport athletes across
the entire Globe both professionals all
the way down to in Elite and we saw the
same story they are really bad at
understanding the basics of sleep
knowledge as well as really estimating
their Sleep Quality and the effect it
has so all that to say really worth your
time to do something here I generally
recommend getting a sleep study done at
least once a year but this is really the
model that that consensus paper laid out
so kind of level one is basic sleep
education and I'll talk about more
details of that later why you want to do
it how effective basic sleep education
actually is despite what you may think
and then from there you go on to your
next level and that's some sort of free
or low cost in this case completely free
screening see these are questionnaires
um the one I like the most is called the
athlete sleep screening questionnaire is
as ssq this is a validated study in
athletes again I'm emphasizing that
point because there are lots of
validated sleep questionnaires but this
one is specifically in athletes or high
performers and again that's something
you can deploy to anybody um as often as
you'd like you could use it you know
monthly or once a year daily really if
you wanted to at almost no cost from
there that's going to help you kind of
triage where you put your emphases a
little bit um the model they've got here
is if they identify No Sleep problems
whatsoever in that screener then you go
back to First Step which is you still
continue to educate because sleep
problems can start just because they
don't have one now doesn't mean they
won't have one later and just because
they don't have a sleep problem that
qualifies on that questionnaire doesn't
mean they're not suboptimal doesn't mean
they're not 80% or 90% and as we've
talked about earlier hopefully I've made
the case that even those last few
percentage points absolutely matter so
that's one order No Sleep issues
whatsoever according to the
questionnaire now according to the
questionnaire if they have mild sleep
problems then in that case you can go on
to more advanced questionnaires um the
one here you're going to go after is
called the asbq so athlete sleep
Behavior questionnaire a little bit
different than the previous one um but
this can help you kind of identify um if
some other issues are going on if data
comes back from that and says hey
everything's all clear then you go back
to step one which is education if not
then you may want to invest in some sort
of long-term either sleep log or
wearable tracking device something like
that now you're going on to either
continue to use free tools sleep logs
you know this is just a journal you're
writing stuff down you're tracking how
good you feel you're tracking how bad
you felt your sleep was how long you
slept you know things like that totally
free or you've invested somewhere
between you know maybe a couple of
hundred dollars to five six hundred
bucks on some sort of wearable I'll
cover those here in a
second if we go back to the beginning
now and we've identified from our
asq a a either moderate to severe sleep
issue we've got different steps here now
what's important and I want to say that
one more time is this is not just severe
this is moderate to severe either one of
these get the same next couple of steps
which is you're going to refer to some
sort of sleep specialist um
unfortunately there's not a lot of high
performance um sleep trained people at
this point you're really going to have
to kind of go the medical route but
worth it if they have a medical disorder
um you're going to do some sort of
Consulting and testing then you going go
into differential diagnosis you know do
they have a sleep disorder if so which
one etc etc you're going to treat that
athlete or have the physician treat that
athlete and then go right back to step
one with education so overall as a
framework I think this hopefully has
been helpful um if those of you that are
working with many people either you're
setting up a clinic or a coaching
practice or something like that or even
if you're yourself and you're trying to
figure out man you know should I spend
money on a sleep study should I spend
money on a Tracker or well maybe just
start with these free Visions first and
then if you don't flag for anything you
can continue to just um use uh High
Sleep Quality behaviors and hygiene and
things like that but if you do flag for
anything even what's considered to be
again moderate or severe then maybe
invest exploring into um higher Fidelity
types of analyses now something really
important I want to point out if you
were to use something like the assq in
of itself does not determine whether or
not you have a sleep disorder it is just
information that gives you a likelihood
another ways to say this is hey you
should probably go get checked out from
a true full clinical
analysis well you may be then thinking
to yourself I don't have a sleep
disorder I'm not even going to take the
questionnaire but I'm trying to really
convince you that that's the wrong
approach because like I said a second
ago one prevalence of sleep disorders
are very high in everybody and over 80%
go undiagnosed two we know athletes or
anyone who's really pushing high
performance or physically larger is more
susceptible than the average person 20
to 40% so high numbers right there three
athletes in general are very bad at
understanding and recognizing how poor
their sleep is and that's generally
because there are a ton of signs and
symptoms that you go through and you
deal with in your day that you think are
benign you think are normal you think
that's just how you are you think that's
just how your body is you think you're
tired because you're training so much
you think um you're fatigued and sore
because of what you're doing in practice
and all that is partially true it's all
also signs of sleep disorders So you
you're probably going to be pretty
surprised if you take this questionnaire
at what they're asking and how they can
actually ask these questions and based
on your response to these alone are
validated ways to identify Sleep
Disorders remember that's what validated
means it says when we gave people this
questionnaire and we compared that
directly to the gold standard polography
this is all the wires and electrodes
hooked up to you the full sheam that the
people who score certain way on this
questionnaire also then have actual
Sleep Disorders that's what it means to
be validated okay so again I would still
say you know get that doubly verified
but that's what it really means okay so
if you start looking through the
questions and you start seeing things
like do you snore most people just think
that is a normal thing or it's not a big
deal when in reality it is it is a not a
guarantee but it is a sign of sleep
disorder how much caffeine do you use
how rested do you feel throughout the
day we talked earlier about other
symptoms like it shouldn't not take you
more than 20 minutes to fall asleep at
night that's your sleep latency another
commic sign how hard is it to get to
sleep how long does it take you to fall
asleep um you shouldn't wake up with
there's going to be some inertia in the
morning a little bit of grogginess but
it shouldn't be extreme it shouldn't be
prevalent you should not be able to fall
asleep all day at any point in time
throughout the day those are other
common science sords so it is some very
basic questions and you may be thinking
to yourself oh yeah I don't have a sleep
disorder I don't sleep as much as I want
or maybe a little bit slower but I wake
up really tired all day oh yeah I do
snore oh yeah I I'm fatigued um I wake
up more than once per night most nights
all of these are signs of if not
clinical sleep disorders certainly
suboptimal sleep that all said I hope I
didn't dramatize or overly attempt to
scare you and thinking you all have
Sleep Disorders it's not the case
it's just more the point of look this is
an opportunity for some pretty
tremendous performance enhancement the
likelihood of you having worse sleep
than you think is reasonably High and
the cost here is nothing takes a few
minutes to do easily scalable the
solutions are easy to find in terms of
how you scored and so to me it just
seems to land on the boy we should
absolutely do this the benefit is really
huge and the cost is quite low okay so
to recap for most people starting off
with a questionnaire is a really good
strategy now the upside of it as we
mentioned is it's free quick and easy to
interpret the downside of it is it's
really just subjective data it's not an
objective look at what's actually
happening to do that you've got to go to
the next level you're introducing some
cost there but you're going to trade
that off for accuracy so the next kind
of Step Up which is in this moderate
again usually two to you know $400 $500
range is using what's called actigraphy
Fe these are your wearables all right
I'll talk about the pros and cons of
those in just one second so those
commercially available devices are
objective um some but most aren't
clinically validated or FDA approved to
actually be able to diagnose Sleep
Disorders but some are but they have
other value and stuff that I'll talk
about here in one second the highest
level up and now you're talking the most
cost the most invasive but most accurate
are clinical sleep studies this is used
as a technology for the most part called
polysomnography and this can be done at
home or in a clinic and there are many
pros and cons to that as well so what
I'd like to do now is really quickly
talk about each of these different
objective methods discuss the pros and
cons so you can make the best decision
possible for you in your given scenario
I'm going to start off with polygraphy
or what I'll refer to from here out is
PSG now some of the benefits here are it
has a ton in fact more than anything
else data behind it so there's a lot of
comparisons you can make there's a lot
of science there's a lot of support and
you can really get a true sense of
what's going on it is objective it is
something that can be done in your home
or in a hospital setting um now the
hospital setting is the overwhelming
majority of psgs but more and more
companies are and Technologies are
coming on board that allow you to do
this from your home and so the ability
to diagnose and interpret clinical sleep
disorders is really high here the
downside though is you know it's kind of
the same thing as the upside one if
you're doing this in a you know hospital
or clinical setting it's not a realistic
picture of what's happening in your life
it's you're not going to sleep the same
when you've got these electrodes hooked
up to you and you're in a funky bed um
you're probably only going to be able to
do it one or two maybe three nights and
so we're getting maybe not a great
picture of exactly what's happening
we're also basically scanning just for
disorders and so if you don't meet those
certain thresholds which are honestly
somewhat arbitrary then you may be kind
of basically told hey you're fine this
is similar to the X-ray thing I talked
about earlier so they're coming in
saying hey I don't see a broken bone so
you're fine but just cuz your bone isn't
broken doesn't mean your joints
functioning correctly either and so
there's some downside there they tend to
be pretty costly and the the weight line
can be very long but they are again the
most accurate picture and because they
are clinical then you're able to work
with a physician that can help you treat
anything if you do have something that
is worthy of medical consideration so a
lot of prosen cons to that if we move to
the PSG in home you know still pretty
expensive typically still people are
only doing a night or two maybe three of
that but we're getting a more realistic
uh picture and setting of that so um
options are available depending on where
you're at sometimes you can get it
covered from insurance which is nice and
other times not but PSG would generally
be the gold standard now another way to
approach sleep at the highest standard
is to use a method called
cardiopulmonary coupling now this has
actually been around for long time it's
got dozens and dozens of studies behind
it though most people have never heard
of it it's a little bit different than
PSG a approaches different things it has
a different Target it's looking more at
your physiology your autonomic nervous
system your respiratory rate and things
like that um it was developed by Dr
Robert Thomas uh from Harvard and again
it's been studied in a lot of areas it's
FDA approved as a way to diagnose Sleep
disorders and so there are some pros and
cons to each of these approaches I would
recommend if you're interested in that
to talk to your physician or medical
team to decide which approach PSG or CPC
is better for you based on the questions
you have and trying to get answered but
I wanted to make sure you knew that both
of those options are available taking it
down to the next level is what we call
actigraphy there are commercially and
research grade available devices to be
candid with you we use the research
grade ones a lot and more and more of
those are actually becoming commercially
available and so that's something to pay
attention to but the other ones uh
you're more familiar with these watches
and rings and uh wrist straps and chest
straps and different things like that
that can be used depending on which one
you want to talk about the data are
quite different they all have their own
you know unique value benefits and
things like that I don't want to get
into the details of all those um quite
right now but I think globally you can
think about actigraphy or wearables as
hey they are a couple of $100 and they
have generally some pros and cons many
of them are pretty accurate at measuring
things like whether or not you're asleep
and in fact some of them are really
accurate over 90 95 some of them higher
than that percentage accuracy of
measuring when you're asleep measuring
when you're awake becomes more
challenging and so they tend to have
problems in those areas those can range
between like 50 to 80% accuracy again
really depending upon the DI you're in
so using it to identify whether you're
asleep or not great but past that we
start to get into problems now the
reason I don't want to honestly spend a
lot of time here is because I believe
even the technology I think it's going
to get better so I'm not super concerned
that either any of those given devices
are at 90% because I probably going to
figure they're going to be 95% soon
enough anyways or closer than that and
so it's really not that big of a deal at
the current moment the issues with
actigraphy I think are different and
that is really they're trying to put
together with the best intentions
Collective scores for optimization for
quality and as we talked about earlier
that is very challenging um I don't
necessarily need or want or should have
the same amount of time in each and one
of my sleep stages it's probably
dependent upon what I'm doing and in
fact sleep stages themselves have some
problems maybe that's a conversation for
another day but if you poke into the
research here you'll find plenty of
sleep scientists who just fundamentally
disagree with the idea of trying to
optimize or maximize a certain amount of
time spent in slow wave sleep or deep
sleep versus rem or things like that we
don't necessarily know what those
optimal numbers are we definitely don't
know what they are in athletes there's
no data on that almost whatsoever and so
really being overly concerned with your
score on your wearable is where problems
start to come in and in fact there is
something that's that's growing in this
community called orthosomnia which is
insomnia that is induced by people
trying to optimize their score on
wearables and so I don't want to paint a
bad picture here because wearables can
be incredibly beneficial uh we we see
tons of evidence of people getting
better at their sleep simply because
they're more accountable they are more
calibrated they thought they were
getting more sleep than they actually
are they're tend to make better habits
and choices because they know they're
going to look at their score in the
morning and they and they want to get
better and so this is not all bad it is
like anything else we've talked about
and like anything else we probably will
talk about ever in this podcast and
that's pros and cons right so way the
downside with the balances it's maybe
not as accurate but it's an order of
magnitude cheaper and instead of of
having to do one or two nights you can
now do every single night at the same
time maybe there's problems with that
you don't necessarily want everyone I I
could tell you countless stories of
athletes and clients I've worked with
where we take their trackers away from
them or maybe we keep them tracking but
we block their ability to see their own
score because it just leads to all kinds
of problems and so it's a viable option
use what's best for you in your
situation okay so at this point
hopefully I've covered a tool that's
accessible for just about everybody
listening here we talked about screeners
which are completely free to low
moderate cost wearables all the way up
to the highest standard of either
polysomnography or cardiopulmonary
coupling testing done at your home or in
a sleep lab also to continue on with
that I'll share with you a little bit
about what we do with our professional
athletes and Elite Executives that
really don't have time or cost
limitations but want the best possible
solution what we actually do is build
full functioning sleep labs in their
home as as well as a scalable version
that they can take on the road so we are
running FDA approved clinical sleep
studies on them almost every single
night and we're measuring everything
about their sleep uh we're doing things
differently based on their sport so our
golfers go through a little bit
different protocol than our UFC fighters
and that's different than our major
league baseball players Etc and so the
testing that things we're measuring and
monitoring are slightly different and
all that tells us in the highest Val
possible how they are sleeping but we
also care about why they're sleeping
that way so as a part of that we're
running four separate analyses so we're
always looking at the environment uh
hopefully by the time you're listening
to this U my paper's been published so
we've got a literature review out right
now in review and that covers 11 unique
factors like CO2 and a bunch of other
things that are involved in your
environment um that can be influencing
your sleep and explaining why you're
sleeping the way you are outside of that
there's physiology so there's a bunch of
specific sleep blood work and blood
panels that we've created um things that
go after thyroid and iron and um a bunch
of other stuff that you may be not
paying attention to there's a behavioral
component to it and there's also
psychology so all four of those unique
components are going to tell us why
you're sleeping the way you are so we do
this again pretty extensively and the
reason we put so much effort and energy
into this is well everything I've been
talking about it is really a huge
performance magnifier so Solutions like
that are available for those folks that
uh want to go to the end degree here
with their sleep optimization so now
that we' fully investigated or analyzed
our sleep how do we interpret the
results so let's move on to our second
eye there please also remember we're not
talking about how do I interpret my
sleep from a risk of disease later in
life or anything like that we're talking
about how do I interpret it from the
perspective of maximizing performance so
what should my sleep look like if I'm
trying to get the Optimal Performance
results in terms of duration the number
seems to be about 9 hours of course
there's lots of individual variation
here some folks May truly be at their
best at 8 hours or seven and a half and
some might actually need nine or 10 but
nine seems to be the number that came up
a lot in the research also in my
conversations with these sleep X where
it's like Amy Bender and Steven lley and
Jeff durmer they all basically came back
and kept saying 9 hours so I think
that's a pretty good starting place in
terms of other metrics of quality we
mentioned latency 5 to 15 minutes seem
to be the sweet spot if your latency
again this is time it takes you to fall
asleep at night is under 5 minutes this
is probably an indicator of the fact
that you're underslept if it's longer
than that we're probably in an area of
maybe suboptimal sleep routines or
habits or environments or something like
that it's delaying us from getting into
sleep we also may be doing something
throughout the day like excessive
caffeine training too hard too late at
night or other issues like that that are
Ling our time to
sleep efficiency if you're getting that
metric on your wearable um you're going
to see again the medical numbers are say
hey be above 85% I personally and this
is just my Andy's interpretation here I
always like to see it above
93% efficiency is generally a problem of
sleep latency um or waking up too often
throughout the night those are the two
biggest contributors and so I I want to
see that number above 93 if I can above
95% wa events I've already talked about
it is absolutely normal to wake up once
a night but we're not trying for normal
here I actually my goal is to get people
to sleep through the night every night
in other words say I don't want you
waking up at all that's the target we
should be able to sleep through the
night on most nights that doesn't mean
if you're waking up every night you've
got a disorder or anything close to that
again we're pushing for optimal here as
you age this gets more challenging but
certainly waking up twice or more per
night um is almost always in my book
going to be suboptimal sleep and then
finally we want to have some subjective
measures of how are you feeling how does
that make you perform the next day so
how is your daytime sleepiness I want
you waking up with a little bit of sleep
inera but not a ton I want you to feel
pretty refreshed when you get when you
wake up you're going to be a little bit
sleepy throughout the day especially
early afternoon but I don't want you
walking around all day the ability to
fall asleep on command Okay so daytime
sleepiness is how we kind of coxes so
for me that's the general picture of
what I'm looking at for Sleep Quality
now I need to mention this again because
it comes up so commonly and that is your
sleep stages people are very concerned
about how much time they spend in say
deep sleep or REM sleep or any other
styles of sleep now this becomes really
challenging and I have to be honest with
you in my coaching experience I've
generally found this to be more
problematic than it is helpful doesn't
mean it's hasn't helped some but this
causes a lot of issues I mentioned
earlier it's somewhat arbitrary most uh
wearables are taking a measure of your
sleep kind of once every five minutes or
so and then they're arbitrarily defining
your sleep based on 30 second Epoch or
time domains and they're using standards
that are really really old in this case
40 plus years old and they change
sometimes the scientific Community says
okay now this thing is defined as N2 or
N3 or whatever or sometimes they take
them out entirely and so it just hasn't
been that helpful to worry about I
generally feel like if you pay attention
to the other stuff your sleep behaviors
your sleep environment your sleep um
relationship in general what we want to
do is not have you obsess over some
arbitrary or in this case sometimes
proprietary uh equivalence of
optimization meaning depending on which
company you bought it from they Define
optimal differently and there's not even
a scientific consensus of that so we're
really chasing a rabbit that may not
actually be something we want to go
after and so I don't want to be too
negative here but really people have
worked themselves into a bit of a tissy
here trying to optimize the Sleep based
on those trackers when I don't think
that's the best case use for them
there's a lot of benefit from trackers
like we've talked about
earlier but I'm just generally going to
caution you against this one in my
personal coaching experience we talked
about how they are problematic in terms
of accuracy some better than others and
they're getting better but they're not
there and why this really matters is
there have been some studies that have
looked and in fact Stephen lley stuff
have looked at things like sleep
deception so imagine being in a study
and being told you either slept for 5
hours when you actually slept for eight
or the opposite and that research is
pretty clear you will perform the next
day based upon what you think you slept
rather than what you actually slept so
imagine what's happening when you're
getting false or inaccurate information
from your tracker it is absolutely
impacting how you're performing the next
day and so the people that are just like
well I just track and I don't do
anything with it okay we talked about
orthosomnia earlier now we're talked
about the research on Deception this
stuff is making an impact on you and so
we really want to be judicious and
careful with how we're using those
trackers my recommendation again one
more time to be clear here is just
really not to worry too much about the
Sleep staging how much time you spent in
deep or Ram or things like that and pay
attention to the other things sleep
latency sleep Behavior use it for
accountability making better choices
maybe you don't have that extra cocktail
maybe you don't do that other thing you
know is going to be bad for your sleep
because it's going to impact your score
tomorrow to me those are beneficial uses
of it and just really be cautious and
careful of spending too much time
worrying about those sleep stages just
as one final note before we go on to our
third and final eye and that is as
always me wanting to be transparent with
you and share what I do in my coaching
practice if I'm interested or feel like
I need to dive deep into somebody's
Sleep Quality or look at their what
called Sleep architecture I'm going to
use cardiopulmonary coupling of that CPC
we talked about and I'm going to go
after three things and this is not
specifically based on the research it's
honestly my personal experience and the
ones that I found to be most important
and the biggest indicator of opportunity
to improve sleep and those three metrics
are going to be their sleep stability
sleep fragmentation and then finally
their respiratory rate and effort we're
going to talk a lot more about that
third one in future episodes there's a
lot of interesting things there
so to summarize everything about Sleep
Quality a lot of ways you can go about
it Define it how it's most important for
you be careful of the pitfalls and use
it to develop more resilient sleepers
not more sensitive ones with that being
said it's time for us to jump into our
third and final eye and that's
intervention now frankly we could
probably do an entire episode on
different ways and tactics and tools to
improve sleep but given me this far in
what I'd like to do is just focus on a
handful that have been shown the
research as well as in my own personal
experience to be particularly helpful at
improving sleep duration quality and
timing and so the very first one I like
to start with is maybe not going to
apply to everyone but I think really
important that I don't want to miss and
that is the importance of sleep
education really specifically sleep
education has been shown to enhance
sleep duration by anywhere between up to
20 to 90 minutes uh it reduces sleep
latency by up to 30 minutes can improve
efficiency by over 5% and has been shown
to reduce sleep onset variance by almost
a half an hour and so it's not just
duration its quality as well so really
worth your time there's a lot of
research on what happens to athletes and
individuals sleep duration and quality
when you simply educate them so step
number one is telling your kids and
telling your athletes and telling the
people that you're training and coaching
how important sleep really is I know
what you're feeling it's the feeling I
get when I have to talk about sleep
sometimes man like I'm going to say this
they're not going to pay attention and
it's not going to matter but the
research shows the opposite the research
is really clear when you spend anywhere
between 30 to 60 Minutes educating
people on sleep you can see pretty
important improvements in duration and
quality that lasts up to a month with
just a single session of education and
so this stuff is really important to
talk about you want to teach a handful
of different things number one the value
of screening like we've established
earlier checking out whether or not you
have a this order um the the need for
duration so telling them people don't
know that 9 hours is the number that
sleep scientists recommend for high
performing athletes that fact alone can
change behaviors and then third is
actually sleep hygiene in fact there's a
really cool study on soccer players that
asked them to do very minimal I think it
was about 10 or 15 minutes before they
went to sleep to not use their phone
they used an eye mask and then a couple
of very very standard
noninvasive approaches to sleep and what
they found was the groups that did that
were able to sleep almost an hour and a
half more on the days following a game
so what that means is as anyone who's
played Sports know when you play a night
game it's really hard to sleep that
night it's very common for athletes to
sleep four or five hours after that and
so the group in this study that didn't
do the hygiene steps slept for four and
a half hours on average that night in
the group that did slept for almost six
so they were able to add an hour and a
half of sleep by having them do just a
few very basic sleep hygiene steps but
this really is not um an explanation or
example of the quality of the hygiene
it's the education piece that matters
here just telling them they need to
sleep more and giving them a few tips
really does make a big impact so wanted
to make sure that you have that
information I realize not all of you in
fact probably few of you are coaches but
for those of you that are out there I
wanted you to have that information so
outside of Education the next big rock
to move is opportunity and so this is
really a conversation with you and
yourself for the most part everyone has
the ability to give them themselves more
opportunity to sleep so when we're
talking sleep extension of course just
giving yourself more hours is the
obvious solution how do you do this well
generally we don't like to schedule
things first thing in the morning if
possible I personally don't use an alarm
clock I have not in many many years I
get up very early personally but I don't
schedule things I have to do within the
first couple of hours so I don't have to
have an alarm clock more importantly
probably is getting to bed at a
consistent time shutting things down
earlier if you can avoid night exercise
very late at night avoid working late at
night and things like that if at all
possible that gives yourself the
opportunity another thing to do is
making sure that you are creating what
we call a pro sleep culture this could
be within you and your team if you're
leading individuals and by this don't
think about Just Sports think of this as
running a business business and a
company are you creating a pro or a
negative sleep culture right are you
allowing people the opportunity to
embrace sleeping well or are we still
thinking about poor sleep as you know a
badge of honor if you will in fact
there's a lot of research on this and
how important it is and how impactful it
can be to just promote sleep as a
performance-enhancing tool not just
something getting in the way or you know
taking away training time this is
something that we're going to use as a
competitive Advantage so making sure we
have the opportunity from ourself as
well as the people that we're guiding
and leading to have a pro sleep culture
the next one is what we've talked about
uh a little bit earlier and that is
making sure we have a structured sleep
plan so what I mean by this is when
you're organizing your day like I've
talked about or you're organizing your
team meetings or when you're working out
are you doing it in a way that allows
you the chance to sleep appropriately as
we mentioned before not doing things at
night that we know disrupt sleep if we
can do them earlier in the day are we
giving ourselves the opportunity to bank
sleep prior to Major competitions or
major periods of lost sleep so say
you're traveling a bunch you've got a
heavy workload coming up finals week or
whatever the case may be and you know
sleep is going to be a problem are you
removing things in the 3 days to 30 days
before that that are optional so that
you can maximize sleep in that
particular time in any given day if you
can't get enough sleep are you giving
yourself the opportunity to take take
naps 20 to 90 minute naps are very
effective for performance enhancement
acutely but more importantly to just add
back some of that sleep time so all this
falls under the umbrella of you'll never
sleep enough if you never give yourself
the chance to sleep enough the next set
of solutions really deal with improving
the quality and timing of your sleep
getting started right out the gates the
most important thing you can do to
improve your sleep quality is treating
your sleep disorder if you actually have
one there are a number of really easy
solutions depending upon what your sleep
problem actually is I think about this
from the perspective of a football
player they're probably more likely to
be dealing with things like sleep apnea
because they're larger relative to say
maybe a swimmer whose issue is more
likely to be dealing with circadian
rhythms because they're often times
practicing and training early in the
morning so right out the gates just
thinking about what we're asking our
bodies to do gives us some strategies
for what type of disorder we may likely
have and then of course then the
solution for that in order to make my
Solutions a little bit more
straightforward what I want to do is
talk about getting to sleep faster and
then staying asleep more effectively so
what are the reasons why people struggle
to fall asleep and how can we improve
that it can be a number of different
things the obvious ones but still
important are we using stimulant or
caffeine too late for our own physiology
some folks can metabolize caffeine very
quickly and it doesn't affect them
others really struggle if it's within
you know eight or more hours of sleep it
can affect their overall Sleep Quality
that's a common one a working or doing
any other stimulating events at night
can be a problem where people really
miss this is the best way to probably
think about it is novelty so it's not
the fact that you're on your phone or
the fact that you're watching TV or
anything it's seeking of novelty that
seems to be the big problem so it's okay
for some folks I will be candid with you
I watch a little bit of TV basically
every night before sleep but what you
don't want to do are things that cause
you to seek novel
and so your phone becomes problematic
because something new will pop up and
it'll reward that pattern of seeing
something new and novel and get you
excited and so what you don't want to do
is watch TV shows that are that you
don't want to watch things that are
aggravating or arousing or exciting you
want to watch typically things that are
more interesting but not overly
stimulating uh this is planet Earth this
is uh not murder mysteries this is not
um things that get you aggravated and
irritated like the news and political
events and things like that and so um
that is what you want to be cautious of
eating too close to bed can be a problem
however however and this is important
people miss this there is excellent
research showing small snacks before bed
can enhance Sleep Quality and reduce
sleep latency specifically kiwis are are
well studied as effective sleep aids um
higher glycemic index meals pretty close
to bed again low amounts can be great we
certain certainly don't want to eat high
amounts and increased digestion or heart
rate and problems like that but small
snacks for some people can actually be
really effective at putting you to sleep
probably most important to all this
though is really the pattern and if you
look around at any the Sleep research or
talk to Sleep Experts they're going to
talk about the need to make sure that
your sleeping environment is really a
sleep Sanctuary arm body has probably
one tool better than anything else and
that's the ability to pattern recognize
and this becomes a problem if you go
into two sleep environments and you're
anticipating a pattern of sleep issues
then that pattern is going to persist if
you have the opposite then that pattern
will persist so what we see a lot of
times our solution strategies for people
having a hard time going to sleep
despite the fact that they're doing all
these other things right and this is
common right oh I don't have caffeine I
stop working um you know many hours
before I don't eat before I meditate
before I do breath work I do all these
things and I still struggle with sleep
okay great I'm not watching TV all those
other why am I still struggling to fall
asleep well often times it's the fact
that you think about struggling to fall
asleep that's causing that pattern to
persist so how do we solve that we take
clocks away you don't get to measure and
you don't get to see your sleep score
you don't get to see your sleep latency
number you don't get to look at the
clock and think about how long it's
taking you to fall asleep so all of
those are also tools to take that out of
the equation and reframe the approach
into thinking when I get into bed this
is an awesome opportunity to sleep
rather than oh my gosh I'm going to get
into bed and have another night where I
can't fall asleep that's a bad framework
to be in and you want to get out of that
as quickly as you possibly can these
environmental pattern recognition things
are so strong you can actually use it to
your advantage especially when traveling
everyone knows of the first night effect
which is when you are in a new
destination you struggle to sleep the
first night but tend to sleep a lot
better the second or third and
subsequent nights well a lot of that is
because you're in a different
environment right we are seeing and
smelling and hearing the same things we
did house so if we can artificially
create that in our house and take that
on the road we can dramatically improve
our Sleep Quality and specifically our
sleep onset um think about smell as the
easiest one if you take a scent that you
like common ones are lavender and you
put a little lavender on your bed at
night in your house every night you
stend to associate that smell with safe
secure high quality sleep Etc you take
that on the road with you then put that
on your new mattress or bed or wherever
you go those same s will kick in the
same pattern recognition will happen and
ideally you have the same quality of
sleep you can do a similar thing with
temperature right if you have a set
temperature of your bed you may not be
able to take that entire cooling
mattress with you on the road but there
are things like cooling pillows so you
use that same temperature on your pillow
at home take that pillow or pillowcase
with you and now you have a mimicked
environment you combine a couple of
different things like that and you
should really improve your sleep latency
when you're on the road now when it
comes to staying asleep at night there's
a bunch bunch of different solutions we
can talk about one of my most common
ones is hydration if you drink too much
water of course you're going to wake up
and have to urinate and that's going to
cause you to get up a whole bunch but
really some folks don't
understand that Sleep Quality will be a
big determinate upon how frequently you
get up to go pee if you waking up more
than once and you go to pee there's a
large volume there it is clear and
that's happening the next morning as
well when you wake up and you still have
a lot of pee then you probably are in
issue of drinking too much pure water in
that case just reduce your water intake
for a couple of hours prior to bed and
you should be fine funny enough we've
had plenty of our high performing
clients um our high performing
Executives and our coaching programs
come to us with all kinds of problems
with their physiology and performance
and brain fog and really all of it
boiled down to the fact that they drank
way too much water at night it was
tanking their sleep we moved that and
within days um they're sleeping for 10
hours for the first time in 15 years and
I I have so many examples of that where
it's pretty silly honestly where I'm
like man you spent a lot of money and
time to figure out you drink way too
much water at night so it can be quite
that simple other times though is a
little bit deceiving so folks will
oftentimes think that's the problem if
it's not the case you're waking up and
there's not a lot of volume there or
there is like one time and the second
time it's you know a lot less or it's
you know more yellow colored or in the
morning you wake up and realize you
didn't even pee for 45 minutes after
waking up this is sometimes an issue of
Sleep Quality and so what happens is
typically at night you're supposed to be
sending signals to your kidneys that
says hey stop filtering and producing
urine and so obviously we don't want to
be waking up to do that all throughout
the night if you're of a low quality
sleep though for any number of reasons
that signal can continue to be sent and
so you can continue to make the urine
and so people think that their Sleep
Quality is being ruined by the fact that
they have to get up and pee when their
honest reality is they're peeing because
they're already basically awake and so
that is another way to figure out H
maybe I have a disorder maybe I should
get checked out maybe something is going
on because I'm waking up to pee a lot
and really there's not a lot there I
probably should get checked out another
really common one is sleep position we
see this routinely where 80 plus
percentages of people's sleep problems
happen when they're on one position of
their body most commonly it's your back
and so avoiding sleeping directly on
your back and sleeping either on your
sides as a blanket rule though not true
for everyone um can really dramatically
improve people's sleep I've told this
story earlier uh of one of my
professional athletes I worked with
having this issue but we have seen this
time and time again so getting some
assessment or analysis of what's
happening in your sleep position um this
is a similar story to ergonomics so
making sure that your bed and mattress
and pillow are all comfortable can also
be really important factors uh to your
overall Sleep Quality outside of that we
start now talking about environmental
factors you probably have heard at
nauseum about of course temperature um
you want to be comfortable there and we
want to be probably a little bit cooler
than we are during the day but even
noise we want to be less than 35 DB
anything above that tends to create
problems this is where actually things
like pink noise start to come into play
there's a lot of really interesting
research coming out on that um it's a
little bit deeper than white noise and
it's not really publicly available for
the most part but the research thus far
is quite impressive the issue with like
white noise or sleep machines is the
fact that above 35 decimal they can
actually create sleep problems because
they're so loud and so while it's great
to kind of drown out the background
information you don't want to be in a
position where you're actually too loud
depending on where you live if you're
especially in an urban environment and
you have lots of external um sound stuff
going on you may want to actually turn
into something like earplugs instead of
a sleep machine for that purpose though
earplugs May create problems with ear
pain and discomfort and stuff like that
so again choose the best tool um that
that you have for your situation but
really below 35 decimal is the gold
standard there again ideally in the show
notes here we've got the link to my
paper that you can go through all 11
factors but other ones that are really
common are CO2 there's emerging evidence
that when that thing gets above 900
parts per million and then really
specifically in in in exaggerated
scenarios of above like 2400 parts per
million that this can dramatically
impact Sleep Quality sleep onset and
sleep latency as well as next day
wakefulness memory and decision- making
and a bunch of other cognitive
performance tasks so um many many other
factors that go into your Sleep Quality
such as your environment and that we'll
have in the show notes last thing I want
to talk about here is snoring now I
don't want to overly concern you
everybody snores at some point or
another it doesn't necessarily mean it
probably doesn't mean you have a sleep
disorder though it's not totally benign
if you're chronic or excess store that
that's really the problem here it's not
a normal function it's common but it's
not normal now one thing that's actually
quite funny that I we laugh about on my
team a lot is how frequently people come
into our programs because of sleep
issues and they've tried everything
they've done all the stuff we've talked
about they've had sleep studies done
before and they came back either like
really moderate or nothing at all and
they they maybe think their testosterone
is low or maybe it is and they just like
they've through everything like I just
cannot sleep and we do one little test
on him and realize wow has your sleep
partner been assessed like oh my sleep
partner just snores like crazy and we
always chuckle because I'm like man I
got really bad news for you your sleep
is fine but your partner's sleep is a
complete disaster and they're ruining
your sleep so we've had a lot of people
come into our program and then basically
switch so the person that paid initially
said don't even do me anymore do this on
my sleep partner my husband or my wife
or whatever fix their sleep and then
that original person's sleep disorder
quote unquote goes away immediately and
permanently and this this happen like
you can hear me literally laughing
because it's happen so many times and I
don't feel bad about it cuz the people
sleep perfectly afterwards because we
found the real problem and it had
nothing to do with them and so snoring
can be a real problem with sleep and so
really making sure that it's not you
it's not your sleeping partner or in a
lot of the cases it's their dog um not
often cats are snoring that loud but
dogs that's really really common and so
that that can be really disruptive to
overall sleep if it is you personally
we'll go back to that example you can
try just going with something like mouth
tape I've done that a ton I use it a ton
uh especially using a combination of
nasal dilators so either nasal strips or
something like that to open up your
nasal passageways as well as mouth tape
and and I will be CED with you we we've
had a lot of success with that and
sometimes that step alone really can
improve snoring and and solve AOC ofy
problems it doesn't always happen though
so if it doesn't then you probably need
to go to the next step one way or the
other but it can absolutely be a viable
solution and is a nice place to start
and just to be really clear the next
step I'm talking about is usually
getting a sleep study done but you can
try other stuff as well we've already
talked about position is another common
solution generally people don't snore on
their sides if they do not nearly as
much or as loud as they are when they're
on their back so just try investing in
one of those sleep pillows I talked
about earlier that forces you to sleep
on your left or right side sometimes
that solves the problem immediately um
there are also tongue exerc exercises
you can do we can actually have a whole
protocol here in the show notes uh this
is very free it it's going to take
typically four to8 weeks to have some
sort of an effect but there is strong
research behind tongue strengthening
exercises to resolve that problem
sometimes there is no solution it is
anatomical and you either have to have
some sort of nasal surgery or put in
some sort of mouthpiece uh to resolve
that problem and then sometimes not even
that works but for the most part
something in that solution I just went
over uh is going to either dramatically
help if not completely solve your
snoring problems I'd like to finish with
a couple of quick tips for Sleep timing
now mostly we're thinking about this in
the context of jet lag if you're
interested in that I'd recommend
checking out Dr Andrew huberman's
excellent podcasts and toolkits on that
you can go to hubman lab and just search
jet lag protocols and he's got a bunch
of free information on optimizing and
maximizing performance through jetl you
can also use the app I me mentioned
earlier uh Steven lley time shifter
again no affiliation there but really
what I want you to pay attention to is
not creating jet lag in your own self
and what I mean by that is making sure
your sleep timing is consistent we
generally like to look at 45 minutes
maybe up to an hour at most of waking
and going to sleep and so if you are you
know waking up at 6:00 a.m. during the
weekdays and then you're sleeping in
till 10: a.m. on the weekends you're
effectively creating a 4-Hour time shift
every single weekend that's going to be
highly problematic it's almost no
different than you getting on a plane
and changing time zones every single
weekend and so really being consistent
with your waking time is the best
strategy I like to Anchor that it's the
easiest one to manipulate it's hard to
force yourself to go to sleep when
you're not tired at night but you can
always wake up at or close to the same
time so although you may want to sleep
in many times you can do that but try to
keep it within an hour so if you need
more sleep outside of that try to go to
bed earlier the next night or perhaps
add in a nap like we've talked about
earlier if you're really going to be
extending your transition I would use
the more diligent approach and I would
like to finish here because I think this
culminates in exactly what I've been
talking about the entire episode here
and that is using sleep to our advantage
for performance enhancement it is
creating optimal plans based on unique
and specific solution and treating it
like the true performance enhancing
variable it is and this is how the
United States weightlifting team handled
sleep prior to the 2020 Olympic Games
Japan now as we talked about earlier if
you don't handle this appropriately not
only are you missing out on performance
games but you're having a serious
competitive disadvantage so all the
diligence and attention you put into
your training for the years ahead of
that and your nutrition and your
physical therapy and your mental health
and everything else like that can
completely be smashed by a bad sleep
transition approach the the data are
overwhelming here and so what they did
was number one they hired a full-time
sleep consultant and they built them out
a sleep plan that started 6 weeks prior
to the Olympic Games they did three
weeks at home where they transitioned
and got them on a training light and
eating time that was on Hawaii time and
the reason they did that is because they
went to Hawaii spent 3 weeks there and
then transitioned over to Japan and so
remember six weeks total here so three
weeks at home to get on to Hawaii time
again three things they manipulated was
their exercise draining their light
exposure and their food they then moved
over to Hawaii they spent 3 weeks there
getting then on Japanese time so by the
time they left Hawaii and got to Japan
they were already on optimized Japanese
time this allowed them to then land and
remember this was during covid so they
couldn't hang out in the Olympic Village
for all the time like they typically we
did these athletes were often times
competing 2 to three days maybe 5 days
at the most from when the time they
landed in Japan before that time they
were on their Podium so to me that again
that was a great example of taking
taking sleep seriously and making sure
we're not only not ruining our
performance but optimizing it and
getting the most out of our system so to
wrap everything up let's summarize what
we talked about today we started off by
going over the power and benefits of
physical performance and strength and
power and reaction time as well as
onfield performance so accuracy of
shooting and things like that to
actually winning more games but it
extends beyond that we're really talking
about the ability to maximize our
physical performance in any domain or
capacity in which we're asking our body
to perform remember as always if you
have a body you're an athlete and we all
want to perform at our best and it would
not make any sense for us to think that
sleeping okay is okay we want to sleep
great so that we perform great in doing
that we talked about three major areas
sleep duration Sleep Quality and sleep
timing and how various strategies can be
used based on our own individual needs
and demands to create specific solutions
to maximize all three of those areas of
sleep to get the best out of our body
that we can we also talked about how
that can help us recover from injury
faster and as always we covered a
combination of free to moderate to what
the best in the world are doing for the
three eyes that is how do I investigate
or analyze my sleep how do I interpret
it and then how do I intervene to make
changes on it I hope you enjoyed all
this and that you don't use any of it
against me when your athletes are
competing against mine cuz I want to win
thank you for joining for today's
episode our goal is to share exciting
scientific Insight that helps you
perform at your absolute best if the
show resonates with you and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave up to a
five-star review given that we're a new
podcast subscribing and leaving a review
really really does help us a lot second
please check out our sponsors the show
would not exist without them and they
really are exceptional products and
services and then finally you can share
today's episode with a friend who you
think would enjoy it if you have any
content questions or suggestions please
put those in the comment section on
YouTube I really do try to read these
and see what you have to say if you have
yet to sign up for our monthly
newsletter you can do so at perform
podcast.com our newsletter provides
episode summaries with the key takeaways
for each and every episode EP of the
podcast this includes topics like how to
improve your V2 Max how to build muscle
mass and muscle strength how to optimize
your sleep for high performance and much
more to sign up just go to perform
podcast.com click newsletter at the top
of the screen and then enter your email
address once you sign up you receive
access to all of our newsletters I use
my Instagram and Twitter also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms thank you
for listening and never forget in the
famous words of Bill Bowerman if you
have a body you're an athlete